Finding Mr. Huang: A Missing Hiker in Taiwan's Mountains Nearly Forgotten
谷關失蹤登山客
This is a story about a man who found peace in the mountains.
這是關於一個在山裡找到平靜的男人的故事
He hiked alone exploring the peaks in Taiwan's mountains.
他獨自登山，探索台灣的群峰
One day he never came home.
有一天，他再也沒有回家
And for seven weeks almost nobody looked for him.
在七個星期裡，幾乎沒有人尋找他
This is also a story about people who cared.
這也是一個關於有人在乎的故事
About a Facebook friend who refused to give up.
關於一位拒絕放棄的臉書朋友
About me going into the mountains to find him.
關於我進入山裡尋找他
And about why searching for the missing truly matters.
以及為什麼搜尋失蹤者如此重要
Petr: This is weird
Petr: 這很奇怪
Petr: This is mine ribbon.  What does it do here? (somebody had to take from Puli area)
Petr: 這是我的路條，它怎麼會在這裡？ （一定有人從埔里那邊拿來的）
September 27th 2025
2025年9月27日
I received a message on Facebook from a woman I didn't know.
我在臉書上收到一位陌生女士的訊息
She was asking for help to find a missing hiker.
她請求幫助尋找一位失蹤的登山客
Her name was Miss Tsai and she explained the situation.
她的名字是蔡小姐，她向我說明了情況
Petr: Something there
Petr: 那邊有東西
A man named Huang Jiong Hong (黃炯宏) had gone missing in the mountains.
一位名叫黃炯宏的男子在山裡失蹤了
He disappeared on August 26th 2025
他在2025年8月26日失蹤
but his car was only found one month later.
但他的車子一個月後才被發現
The car was reported by a local resident who noticed
車子是由一位當地居民通報的
it had been parked too long in the same spot.
他注意到車子在同一個地方停太久了
It was at the parking near trail entry to Defulan Trail (德芙蘭步道口) in Guguan (谷關).
車子停在谷關德芙蘭步道口附近的停車場
I asked her the obvious question - Why did nobody search before?
我問她一個顯而易見的問題——為什麼之前沒人搜尋？
She explained the difficult situation.
她解釋了困難的情況
The family didn't know where he went hiking.
家人不知道他去哪裡登山
Petr: It is just label (fallen informational sign)
Petr: 只是個標示（掉落的告示牌）
Huang lived alone and told nobody about his plans.
黃先生獨自生活，沒有告訴任何人他的計劃
When his car was finally found
當他的車子終於被發現時
it was already more than a month since he disappeared.
距離他失蹤已經超過一個月了
Any tracks or clues or memories of hikers who might have seen him that day would be long gone.
任何足跡、線索或可能在那天見過他的登山客的記憶都已消失無蹤
Petr: Fu*k
Petr: 幹
To find someone in the mountains you must first understand who they are and how they think.
要在山裡找到一個人，你必須先了解他是誰以及他如何思考
Huang Jiong Hong (黃炯宏) was a single man in his early 50s.
黃炯宏是一位50歲出頭的單身男子
He had no wife no children and he lived a quiet solitary life.
他沒有妻子、沒有孩子，過著安靜孤獨的生活
Years ago he had been diagnosed with cancer.
多年前，他被診斷出癌症
During that difficult time his wife divorced him and left.
在那段艱難的時期，他的妻子與他離婚並離開了
He survived the cancer and beat the disease.
他戰勝了癌症並擊敗了疾病
But afterwards he was alone.
但之後，他獨自一人
That's when he discovered something that changed everything.
那時候他發現了改變一切的事物
He found the mountains.
他找到了山
Huang posted often on a big Taiwan Facebook hiking group (肉腳登山隊).
黃先生經常在一個大型台灣臉書登山社團發文
His posts described trails he explored views from peaks
他的貼文描述他探索的步道、山頂的景色
and selfies from the mountains with a cute towel around his neck.
以及他在山裡自拍，脖子上掛著可愛的毛巾
His posts were simple but full of good vibes and people liked the content.
他的貼文簡單但充滿正能量，人們喜歡這些內容
They could see a man who had found peace and purpose through mountain hiking.
他們可以看到一個通過登山找到平靜和目標的人
The family was understandably worried about the situation.
家人對這情況感到擔憂是可以理解的
They didn't want more people getting hurt while searching the dangerous terrain.
他們不希望更多人在搜尋危險地形時受傷
They were concerned about the financial cost of hiring search teams.
他們擔心雇用搜救隊的經濟負擔
They didn't know there are many professionals and volunteers
他們不知道在台灣山區
who search for the missing or help with accidents in Taiwan mountains.
有許多專業人士和志工會搜尋失蹤者或協助山難事故
And slowly they were beginning to accept that he was gone.
而且他們慢慢開始接受他已經走了
Basically they had given up.
基本上，他們放棄了
But Miss Tsai couldn't accept giving up on him.
但蔡小姐無法接受放棄他
She wasn't his girlfriend or even a close friend in real life.
她不是他的女朋友，甚至在現實生活中也不是親密朋友
They were Facebook friends who shared the same passion
他們是臉書朋友，對登山有著相同的熱情
for hiking in the mountains.
都熱愛在山裡登山
And she felt someone had to care enough to keep searching.
她覺得必須有人足夠在乎，繼續搜尋
[watch beeping]
[手錶嗶嗶聲]
⚠ ALARM
⚠ 警報
⚠⚠
⚠⚠
⚠⚠⚠ ALARM
⚠⚠⚠ 警報
(Petr: I was thinking it is earquake warning, but my Garmin watch Detected Incident)
（Petr: 我以為是地震警報 但我的Garmin手錶偵測到事故）
When she contacted me I began studying his case carefully.
當她聯繫我時，我開始仔細研究他的案件
I looked through all his Facebook posts to understand his hiking habits.
我查看了他所有的臉書貼文，以了解他的登山習慣
I could see he used offline maps and knew how to navigate with GPS.
我可以看出他使用離線地圖，知道如何用GPS導航
He hiked carefully and always started early never planning overnight trips.
他謹慎登山，總是早起出發，從不計劃過夜行程
He wasn't a reckless hiker.
他不是一個魯莽的登山客
Petr: Hey, It`s coming here (helicopter)
Petr: 嘿，它正在往這裡飛來（直升機）
October 2nd 2025 (today)
2025年10月2日 （今天）
The family had not hired or even asked me to search
家人沒有雇用我，甚至沒有請我去搜尋
they had basically given up.
他們基本上已經放棄了
I was also busy with our event preparation
我當時也很忙，要準備我們的活動
and with another search for a missing senior near Puli.
還要搜尋另一位在埔里附近失蹤的年長者
But I decided to go anyway.
但我還是決定去
I felt sad for this man who loved the mountains
我為這位熱愛山林的男子感到難過
but was missing with almost nobody searching for him.
但他失蹤了，幾乎沒有人在找他
My initial idea was Dongmao Mountain East Peak (東卯山東峰).
我最初的想法是東卯山東峰
I went there first to survey the area
我先去那裡勘察該區域
and also went to the deep valley behind the peak.
也去了山峰後面的深谷
I continued to the main peak of Dongmao Mountain (東卯山)
我繼續前往東卯山主峰
over a rocky ridge where an accident could happen.
穿越一個可能發生事故的岩稜
I looked for any signs of someone falling from the trail
我尋找任何人從步道墜落的跡象
or any suspicious odor.
或任何可疑的氣味
I checked under cliffs and steep sections where accidents typically happen.
我檢查了通常會發生事故的懸崖下方和陡峭路段
The problem was clear - the search area was simply too huge.
問題很明顯——搜索區域實在太大了
I couldn't just search randomly through such steep and dangerous terrain.
我不能只是在這麼陡峭和危險的地形中隨意搜索
I needed more information
我需要更多資訊
to narrow down where the accident most likely occurred.
來縮小最可能發生事故的範圍
Petr: Oh, Fu*k (the rock is loose)
Petr: 喔，靠（石頭是鬆的）
I even flew my drone over the landslide areas to get a better view.
我甚至在崩塌區域上空飛無人機以獲得更好的視野
When searching for missing people
在搜尋失蹤者時
I also need to consider a difficult topic - suicide.
我也需要考慮一個困難的話題——自殺
It's crucial to understand if we're looking for a lost hiker
了解我們在尋找的是迷路的登山客
or someone who had an accident
還是發生意外的人
or someone who went to the mountains with different intentions.
或是帶著不同意圖進入山裡的人是很關鍵的
This changes everything about how and where to search.
這改變了搜尋的方式和地點
From what I learned about Huang's habits and his positive posts about hiking
從我對黃先生習慣和他關於登山的正面貼文的了解
this seemed unlikely.
這似乎不太可能
But I couldn't completely rule it out without more information.
但在沒有更多資訊的情況下，我無法完全排除這種可能性
Then came an important breakthrough. (couple days later)
然後出現了一個重要的突破（幾天後）
Miss Tsai and her brother managed to access Huang's Google account.
蔡小姐和她的哥哥成功登入了黃先生的Google帳戶
In his search history from August 26th they discovered:
在他8月26日的搜尋記錄中，他們發現了：
"東卯山6連峰" - Dongmao Mountain Six Peaks traverse.
「東卯山6連峰」——東卯山六連峰縱走
This detail told me everything I needed to know about his intentions that day.
這個細節告訴了我關於他那天意圖的一切
He didn't just want to hike the main trail to Dongmao Mountain.
他不只是想走東卯山的主要步道
He wanted to visit all peaks the less common directions.
他想造訪所有山峰，走較不常見的路線
And it meant he went there to hike not for other reasons.
這意味著他去那裡是為了登山，而不是其他原因
I also made a detour to the steep trail of the Southeast Peak (東卯山東南峰).
我也繞道去了東卯山東南峰陡峭的步道
But I found nothing that day.
但那天我什麼也沒找到
I asked Miss Tsai if the family could obtain the cell phone tower records.
我問蔡小姐，家人能否取得手機基地台記錄
This data is very helpful for mountain searches because it can tell us much more
這些數據對山區搜索非常有幫助，因為它可以告訴我們更多資訊
even if not directly the exact location.
即使無法直接告訴我們確切位置
The police had shared one piece of information with the family:
警方與家人分享了一條資訊：
The last cell signal was on August 30th at 12:11 PM.
最後的手機訊號是在8月30日下午12點11分
The last cell tower location was on East Guan Road.
最後的基地台位置是在東關路上
The signal direction was 230 degrees from that tower. (azimut is usually wrong)
訊號方向是從該基地台的230度方向（方位角通常不準確）
But I needed more than just the last signal.
但我需要的不僅僅是最後的訊號
I needed the full timeline of tower connections throughout the day.
我需要整天基地台連接的完整時間軸
When did Huang arrive at the trailhead?
黃先生什麼時候到達登山口？
When did his phone signal stop moving between towers?
他的手機訊號何時停止在基地台之間移動？
You see if the cell signal connects to the same tower for many hours without moving it tells us something critical.
你看，如果手機訊號在連續多小時內連接到同一座基地台而不移動，這告訴我們一些關鍵的事情
It means an accident has already happened.
這意味著事故已經發生了
The phone is still turned on and transmitting.
手機仍然開著並傳輸訊號
But the person carrying it can no longer move.
但攜帶它的人已經無法移動
Unfortunately only the last tower connection was known by this point.
不幸的是，此時只知道最後的基地台
For me to do a proper analysis
為了做適當的分析
I would need to see the whole day's data which together with his potential hiking plan
我需要看到全天的數據，結合他可能的登山計劃
would help narrow the search area significantly.
將有助於大幅縮小搜索區域
But the case was already old and these detailed records were not available anymore.
但案件已經太舊了，這些詳細記錄已經無法取得
After my first search day the family finally decided to take action.
在我第一天搜尋之後，家人終於決定採取行動
Huang's father wanted to hire me to help find his son.
黃先生的父親想雇用我來幫助找到他的兒子
They wanted him found and brought home.
他們希望找到他並帶他回家
Based on all the information I gathered
根據我收集的所有資訊
I identified three main hot zones to focus the search:
我確定了三個主要的重點搜索區域：
Zone 1: The ridge area near Defulan Famous Tree (德芙蘭名樹).
第一區：德芙蘭名樹附近的稜線區域
Some hikers had reported an unusual smell in this area
一些登山客報告說在這個區域聞到異味
a few weeks after Huang disappeared.
在黃先生失蹤幾週後
I had been in this area on my first search day
我第一天搜尋時去過這個區域
but hadn't gone deep enough.
但我沒有深入搜索
Zone 2: The Bei Song He Mountain (北松鶴山) area near the parking space.
第二區：北松鶴山停車場附近的區域
There's a trail marked on maps but in reality there is not any trail
地圖上標示有步道，但實際上根本沒有步道
and only steep and dangerous slope.
只有陡峭而危險的斜坡
The terrain here was bad enough that a fall could easily be fatal.
這裡的地形惡劣到足以讓墜落致命
Zone 3: The east side of the trail leading to Dongmao East Peak (東卯山東峰).
第三區：東卯山東峰步道的東側
This area had very steep slopes on both sides of the ridge trail.
這個區域在稜線步道的兩側都有非常陡峭的斜坡
The area where only experienced hikers will go when visiting less common peaks.
這是只有經驗豐富的登山客才會去造訪較少人走的山峰的區域
By this time other SAR volunteers were planning a search during the next weekend.
此時，其他搜救志工正計劃在下個週末進行搜尋
October 11th 2025
2025年10月11日
Day 47 since Huang disappeared.
黃先生失蹤的第47天
I woke up very early that morning and drove from Puli.
那天早上我很早就起床並從埔里開車過來
I had limited time to search
我的搜索時間有限
because we had appointments scheduled that afternoon.
因為我們下午有預約的活動
I only had about 5 to 6 hours total so I needed to search fast and efficiently.
我總共只有大約5到6個小時，所以我需要快速有效地搜索
Right after arriving I went first to Zone 2 -
抵達後，我首先去了第二區
the bad terrain under Bei Song He Mountain.
北松鶴山附近的惡劣地形
I have strong faith though I'm not particularly religious.
我有堅定的信仰，雖然我不是特別虔誠
Sometimes I go to church with my wife and kids.
有時我會和我的妻子和孩子一起去教堂
In past searches where I found missing hikers
在過去找到失蹤登山客的搜索中
I felt like some higher power was guiding me.
我感覺好像有某種更高的力量在引導我
That morning as I prepared to search the dangerous terrain
那天早上，當我準備搜索危險地形時
I prayed silently in my heart.
我在心中默默祈禱
Please help me find this man today.
請幫助我今天找到這個人
I searched through the very steep and broken terrain but found nothing.
我在非常陡峭和破碎的地形中搜索，但什麼也沒找到
Then I went up to Zone 1 the ridge near the famous tree.
然後我上到第一區，名樹附近的稜線
Petr: What here is old ribbon?
Petr: 這裡有舊路條？
I went deeper into the valley under this ridge from both sides.
我深入稜線下方的山谷，從兩側搜索
While we were searching for Huang
在搜尋黃先生時
I kept thinking about what could have prevented this tragedy.
我一直在想什麼可以預防這場悲劇
[stone rumbling]
[石頭滾動聲]
If you hike in Taiwan's mountains
如果你在台灣的山裡登山
please learn from this case and remember these important safety principles:
請從這個案例中學習，並記住這些重要的安全原則：
Always start your hike early in the morning.
總是在早上很早就開始你的登山行程
This gives you plenty of daylight to complete your hike.
這給你充足的日光來完成你的登山
It also gives you buffer time if something goes wrong
也給你緩衝時間，如果出了問題
or takes longer than expected.
或花費的時間比預期長
Huang always followed this rule - he never started late.
黃先生總是遵循這個規則——他從不晚出發
Tell someone your specific hiking plan.
告訴某人你的具體登山計劃
Always let a family member or friend know exactly which mountain you're climbing
總是讓家人或朋友確切知道你要爬哪座山
and which trail you're taking.
以及要走哪條步道
Tell them when you expect to return.
告訴他們你預計何時返回
This is the single most important thing that could have changed Huang's story.
這是最可能改變黃先生故事的最重要的一件事
[sniffing]
[嗅聞]
Because he lived alone and told nobody
因為他獨自生活且沒有告訴任何人
precious weeks were lost before anyone even knew where to search.
寶貴的幾週時間流失了，直到有人知道去哪裡搜尋
Always bring essential safety gear with you.
總是隨身攜帶必要的安全裝備
A waterproof rain jacket definitely helps keep your body temperature stable
防水雨衣絕對有助於保持你的體溫穩定
if weather suddenly changes.
如果天氣突然變化
A headlamp is crucial
頭燈至關重要
because you never know if your hike will take longer than planned.
因為你永遠不知道你的登山行程是否會超過預期時間
Bring extra food and water beyond what you think you need.
帶著比你認為需要的更多的食物和水
These items don't weigh much
這些物品重量不重
but they can make the difference in an emergency.
但它們可以在緊急情況下產生差異
The suspicious smell reported here actually came from these blossoms
這裡報告的可疑氣味實際上來自這些花朵
Taiwan Schima (臺灣木荷).
台灣木荷
Hiker: Hello Petr: Hello
登山客: 你好 Petr: 你好
Use offline maps (GPS) and know how to navigate.
使用離線地圖（GPS）並知道如何導航
Huang did use offline maps and was good at navigation.
黃先生確實使用離線地圖並且擅長導航
But even the best navigation skills cannot prevent every accident.
但即使是最好的導航技能也無法預防每一次事故
A fall a slip on wet rocks
墜落、在濕滑的岩石上滑倒
or some injury - these can happen to anyone.
或某種傷害——這些可能發生在任何人身上
If you do have an accident try to stay in place.
如果你確實發生了事故，盡量待在原地
Hikers should take care of themselves and wait for rescue to arrive.
登山客應該照顧好自己並等待救援到達
Sometimes this means staying in place overnight until help comes.
有時這意味著在原地過夜直到救援到來
[dry branch]
[乾樹枝]
That's why having someone who knows your plan is so critical
這就是為什麼讓某人知道你的計劃如此關鍵
they will send help when you don't return.
當你沒有回來時，他們會派遣救援
I flew my drone along the ridge to survey from above.
我沿著稜線飛無人機從上方勘察
Still nothing conclusive.
仍然沒有確切的發現
Finally I moved down to Zone 3.
最後，我移動到第三區
I climbed the west slope up to the ridge
我爬上西側斜坡到稜線
and then focused on the east side which also matched the phone coverage area.
然後專注於東側，那裡也符合手機覆蓋範圍
The terrain under the ridge was absolutely terrible.
稜線下方的地形真的非常糟糕
Extremely steep slopes covered with unstable rocks
極度陡峭的斜坡上覆蓋著不穩定的岩石
and small creeks cutting through the hillside.
和小溪流穿過山坡
This was dangerous without ropes even for an experienced searcher.
這在沒有繩索的情況下是危險的，即使對經驗豐富的搜救人員來說也是如此
I attempted to descend the east slope to check below the ridge line.
我試圖下降東側斜坡以檢查稜線下方
At one point the terrain became so steep and unstable that I stopped.
在某一點，地形變得如此陡峭和不穩定，以至於我停了下來
I told myself - This is crazy. Turn back now.
我告訴自己——這太瘋狂了，現在轉回去
This is not worth risking your own life.
這不值得冒自己的生命危險
But something made me continue down just a little bit further.
但有些東西讓我再往下走一點點
Just to check what was below this cliff section.
只是想檢查這個懸崖路段下方有什麼
Just to be absolutely sure before I leave.
只是在我離開之前絕對確定
As I carefully descended I started to smell something unusual.
當我小心下降時，我開始聞到一些不尋常的氣味
Petr: I smell something
Petr: 我聞到什麼東西
I've found bodies in the mountains before
我以前在山裡找到過遺體
and the smell is not always intense like people imagine.
氣味並不總是像人們想像的那麼強烈
After 47 days I honestly wasn't sure
47天後，老實說我不確定
if there would even be any smell left at all.
是否還會有任何氣味殘留
I didn't focus too much on the smell but it was there.
我沒有太關注這個氣味，但它確實在那裡
Then I saw something black
然後我看到了黑色的東西
against the ground covered by pine needles.
在被松針覆蓋的地上
A shoe.
一隻鞋子
Decathlon brand size 44.
迪卡儂品牌44號
My hands started shaking as I took a photo.
我拍照時手開始顫抖
I immediately sent it to Commander Lin from the SAR team.
我立即將它傳給搜救隊的林隊長
Does this match what he was wearing? Can you confirm?
這是否與他穿的相符？你能確認嗎？
While waiting for his response
在等待他的回覆時
I began searching the near area very carefully.
我開始非常小心地搜索附近區域
That's when I found a hat.
那時我找到了一頂帽子
It was pink - one of his favorite pink visors
它是粉紅色的——他最喜歡的粉紅色遮陽帽之一
that appeared in so many of his Facebook photos.
出現在他許多臉書照片中
My heart was racing now. This was definitely him.
我的心現在狂跳。這絕對是他
Petr: Here is hat. And there is the shoe.
Petr: 這裡是帽子。那邊是鞋子
I continued climbing down more carefully my mind racing.
我繼續更小心地往下爬，我的思緒飛轉
Then I had to descend through a steep ditch filled with loose stones.
然後我必須穿過一個充滿鬆散石頭的陡峭溝渠下降
Petr: Fu*k I see second shoe.
Petr: 幹，我看到第二隻鞋
Just below where I found the first shoe
就在我找到第一隻鞋的下方
I discovered the second shoe.
我發現了第二隻鞋
Petr: One shoe, second shoe.
Petr: 一隻鞋，第二隻鞋
Petr: OK, You are helping. You are helping OK! (comforting myself)
Petr: 好的，祢在幫助我。祢在幫助我，好的！（安慰自己）
If someone had fallen here they would have tumbled even further down.
如果有人在這裡摔倒，他們會滾得更遠
Petr: hat... shoe.. He must be over there
Petr: 帽子...鞋子...他一定在那邊
Petr: here is  obvious slide
Petr: 這裡有明顯的滑痕
Petr: oh, so deep
Petr: 喔，這麼深
I pushed through the vegetation even though it was difficult to reach.
我穿過植被，即使到達那裡很困難
Through the dense bushes ahead
穿過前方茂密的灌木叢
I could see colors that didn't belong in nature.
我可以看到不屬於大自然的顏色
Something orange. Something blue.
一些橙色的東西。一些藍色的東西
Petr: I have him!
Petr: 我找到他了！
Petr: Over there is orange!
Petr: 那邊有橙色！
Petr: ahh
Petr: 啊
When I got close enough I could clearly see pieces of clothing.
當我靠得夠近時，我可以清楚地看到衣服的碎片
Petr: Sorry!
Petr: 對不起！
Petr: But you are back!
Petr: 但你回來了！
Petr: You will go to family OK!
Petr: 你會回到家人身邊，好嗎！
And then I saw the skull.
然後我看到了頭骨
Petr: Oh my god!
Petr: 我的天啊！
This was Huang Jiong Hong.
這是黃炯宏
After 47 days exposed to the mountain environment
在山中環境暴露47天後
there was almost no flesh remaining on his body.
他的身體上幾乎沒有殘留任何肉
Petr: It must be terrible fall.
Petr: 一定是很可怕的墜落
Petr: The shoes are 20m there and trail is 50m (80m) at least.
Petr: 鞋子在20米那裡，步道至少在50米（80米）
Just bones and some dried darkened skin.
只剩下骨頭和一些乾燥變黑的皮膚
I stopped moving and just stood there for a moment.
我停止移動，只是站在那裡片刻
Petr: Dear heavenly father (pray)
Petr: 親愛的天父（祈禱）
Then I prayed again
然後我再次祈禱
this time out loud my voice breaking the silence of the mountains.
這次大聲說出來，我的聲音打破了山中的寂靜
Rest in peace Mr. Huang. You are found now.
黃先生，願你安息。你現在被找到了
Thank you for letting me find you.
謝謝你讓我找到你
Petr: in the name of Jesus Christ, Amen
Petr: 以耶穌基督的名，阿門
I immediately reported the exact location to the SAR commander.
我立即向搜救隊長報告了確切位置
Huang's body was located approximately 80 meters below the ridge level.
黃先生的遺體位於稜線以下約80米處
The slope was extremely steep - in some sections nearly vertical.
斜坡極其陡峭——在某些路段幾乎是垂直的
I carefully worked my way along the slope
我沿著斜坡小心地移動
searching for any possible route.
尋找任何可能的路線
How do we bring the SAR team back here to recover his body?
我們如何將搜救隊帶回這裡來回收他的遺體？
Eventually I found an old abandoned trail
最終我發現了一條廢棄的舊步道
that had been used for water pipes.
曾經用於水管
Following this overgrown path
沿著這條雜草叢生的小路
I managed to traverse out to the parking area.
我成功橫越到停車場
Commander Lin and some family members were already there
林隊長和一些家屬已經在那裡
waiting for more details.
等待更多細節
Meanwhile others came down and I led the team back up
與此同時，其他人下來了，我帶領團隊返回
through the difficult terrain helping them prepare a safe route out.
穿過困難的地形，幫助他們準備一條安全的路線出來
Later I examined the location more carefully.
後來我更仔細地檢查了位置
The fall didn't happen directly from the trail.
墜落並非直接從步道發生
Huang had missed a sharp turn and continued along the ridge
黃先生錯過了一個急轉彎，沿著稜線繼續前進
then fell from there.
然後從那裡墜落
We'll never know if this happened during the day
我們永遠不會知道這是發生在白天
or under stress when it was getting dark in the mountains.
還是在山中天色漸暗時承受壓力的情況下
This reminds me why it's so important to carry a good headlamp
這提醒我為什麼攜帶好的頭燈如此重要
and plan your route with easier sections at the end.
並且在路線末段規劃較簡單的路段
I wasn't sure where his phone was
我不確定他的手機在哪裡
maybe in the bag or in his pocket or just nearby.
也許在包裡，或在他的口袋裡，或就在附近
But it explained
但這解釋了
why the cell tower signal never moved after the accident.
為什麼事故發生後基地台訊號再也沒有移動
When we finally reached his location
當我們最終到達他的位置時
some brave SAR members put on their protective gear
一些勇敢的搜救隊員穿上防護裝備
to handle the remains.
來處理遺體
They carefully and respectfully packed his remains into a body bag
他們小心且尊重地將他的遺體裝入屍袋
then secured it to a SKED rescue litter.
然後將其固定在SKED救援擔架上
This story is about more than just finding someone who was lost.
這個故事不僅僅是關於找到一個失蹤的人
It's really about the power of caring when others have given up.
它真正是關於當其他人放棄時關懷的力量
Miss Tsai never stopped believing that Huang deserved to be found.
蔡小姐從未停止相信黃先生應該被找到
She was just a Facebook friend
她只是一個臉書朋友
they had never even hiked together in person.
他們甚至從未一起登過山
They connected years ago through their shared love of the mountains.
他們多年前通過對山的共同熱愛而聯繫
But when everyone else had accepted he was gone
但當其他人都接受他已經走了時
she refused to give up on him.
她拒絕放棄他
Many volunteers came to help
許多志工前來幫助
once the search was properly organized.
一旦搜尋得到適當組織
Strangers helping strangers in the mountains.
在山中陌生人幫助陌生人
This is the spirit of Taiwan mountain rescue
這就是台灣山岳救援的精神
people who care about bringing the missing home.
關心將失蹤者帶回家的人們
When I think about Huang Jiong Hong (黃炯宏)
當我想到黃炯宏時
I feel deep sadness mixed with respect.
我感到深深的悲傷和尊敬交織
Years ago the cancer diagnosis and the divorce
多年前癌症診斷和離婚
when he was at his lowest point left him alone.
在他最低谷時讓他獨自一人
But Huang found something that saved him.
但黃先生找到了拯救他的東西
He found peace through hiking in Taiwan's mountains.
他通過在台灣山區登山找到了平靜
Sharing photos on Facebook exploring new peaks
在臉書上分享照片，探索新的山峰
finding simple joy in nature.
在大自然中找到簡單的快樂
In the end these mountains he loved also took his life.
最後，他所愛的這些山也奪走了他的生命
But I believe he died doing what made him happy.
但我相信他死於做讓他快樂的事情
Huang Jiong Hong (黃炯宏) was found on October 11th 2025.
黃炯宏於2025年10月11日被發現
47 days after he disappeared into the mountains he loved.
在他失蹤進入他所愛的山林47天後
His body was recovered by the brave SAR team members
他的遺體被勇敢的搜救隊員回收
and returned to his family.
並送還給他的家人
His elderly parents his brothers with families
他年邁的父母、他有家庭的兄弟們
could finally say goodbye properly.
終於能夠好好告別
Even if you love the mountains
即使你熱愛山林
you should not stay there alone forever.
你也不應該永遠獨自留在那裡
And to Huang Jiong Hong (黃炯宏)
致黃炯宏
may you rest in peace in the mountains that brought you so much happiness.
願你在曾經帶給你如此多快樂的山中安息
You are not forgotten.
你不會被遺忘